I guess we're on uh let me see here.
Yeah, Arya Dear
uh class three, you're going to show me
it
6.17, which is a crying
baby. Okay. Looks like Stanley when he
wakes like Stanley when he wakes up.
Okay. Uh, we're
in chapter
25. Uh, we have three chapters now to
go. 25, 26, 27. We have to finish them
this week. Hopefully, grandpa cannot
talk too much and finish the class. And
we finished the investigation of
the four higher truths. And now we're
going to start the investigation of
Nirvana. Okay. And that's chapter 25. Uh
it's the investigation of Nirvana.
Okay. All right. Let's go to this first
image is
uh the other guy starts with his same
old same old. In English it's called
same
old same old. I'll tell you the I'll
tell you the Sanskrit for fun. Okay.
How if everything's empty and nothing
can start and nothing can stop then how
can you how can you reach nirvana? You
know he's got the same old complaint if
everything's empty. I don't see how
there can be a nirvana. I don't and
specifically I don't see how you can
stop human suffering or sensient
suffering. Uh I don't see how you can
stop it if if there's everything's
empty. If nothing starts and nothing
stops, I don't see how you could reach
Nirvana. And he uses two verbs in in his
uh complaint. He says in Tibetan it's a
bong and gak. Okay. So bong means give
up uh something and gawk means shut the
shut the tap. You shut the flow. Okay.
Give up and shut the flow. Okay. And uh
we have a nice commentary from Chon
Lama. So I'm following Chon Lama
Draash's commentary which is great. And
I got the good carving of it two days
ago. I've been working on it for seven
years. Okay. And that's kind of
frustrating because I have to redo the
whole thing.
Uh we put together Chony Lama's works
were destroyed uh during the cultural
revolution. We we started putting them
back together and we actually sent
someone on a bus to Ch. It's pretty
cool. And he he got uh he finished. His
name is Jason Dunbar. He's an early uh
ALLL guy. He did a great job. And he he
went there at the cost of many diarrhea
sessions.
uh he got a copy of all the books but it
was a terrible terrible copy and one
copy uh came from another city and
anyway we found I was using a bad copy
up to now but we just found a good one
so I have to start the whole thing
over anyway uh he says or to give up
something means
you're negative emotions
And I'm not going to go too much detail
into it, but he
says, so there's a difference between
cllaya, which means negative
emotion, or click
stuff. This computer is clic stuff. It's
part of sanssara, but it's not a
negative
emotion unless I'm late for
class. Okay. Anyway, uh he says give up
basically negativity, mental negativity
and gawk. Gawk is interesting because
classically when you say gobba or gawk,
it means
stopping. And then they always
say the five parts to you that you took
on. the five parts to you that you took
on when you were born. Okay? So, when
you were born, you said you went to the
store and you said, "Oh, this mind looks
pretty good and this body is okay." And
and you made choices and you took on
five pieces. Okay? So, in
nirvana, it's kind of defined
as stopping the five parts to you that
you took on. Okay, which is your body,
your feelings, your capacity to
discriminate between things, all your
other mental
functions and certain little things
about you. And then your main
consciousness, okay, your main mind in
English you can say body and mind. Okay,
the body and mind that you mind body
complex that you took on when you were
born. Okay. So that's stopped in
nirvana. And I'll give you a clue. Okay.
I'll give you a clue. We don't say
nirvana is stopping the five parts of
you. We do say nirvana is stopping the
five parts of you that you took
on. What's the
difference? Yeah. You could have parts
of you that you didn't take on. In other
words, the taking on is the bad part.
Okay? Being forced into a body which
will die is bad. Having a body which
doesn't die is fine. Got it? You can
have the five parts to a person, but you
shouldn't have the five parts to a
person that you took at birth. When you
took birth, you took a you made a
mistake at birth. Actually, you were
forced to. Don't. It's not your fault.
It is your fault.
Anyway, you took a certain body on and
it's and it's a nearly it's a it's a
taken on body and it will die. It has to
die. Okay? Has to get old. Has to die.
Okay? So, he
says Nirvana really has two parts. And
the guardian says nirvana has two parts.
One is get rid of your
negativities and everything involved
with them. And then secondly get rid of
the five parts to you which you took on
your land. Okay that's crucial in this
discussion of nirvana. That's crucial.
Okay. We're
not well we got to talk about it. Okay.
Next picture.
Fancy. Yeah, this one the AI did not too
bad. By the way, Tim, my AI, he's not my
AI has a uh option on it. Uh you can
make a new picture with the AI or you
can say uh show me all the pictures that
anyone ever made about this topic in the
last, you know, since AI started.
When you make an AI picture on almost AI
platforms, you give up the copyright to
it when you make
it, which means they can sell it to
everybody. And uh so you spend a half
hour struggling to get the AI to do what
you want and then they sell your picture
to everybody, but you have to know how
to reach that part of the AI function.
Okay. So anyway, someone else did the
work on this one. I thank you very much.
They always keep the title and it's in
Russian or German or Spanish or Chinese
and it's cool, you know. I forget which
one this one, but anyway, somebody else
made this, but it fits. Okay, I want to
ask you guys today,
uh, where are we going in the flow of
the last three chapters? Okay, we're
sitting here together. You can say last
four chapters. We're sitting here
together. We're here. We're stuck here
for a week
hopefully, unless you break your arm and
go to the hospital.
Uh but
uh so we got four chapters that we're
going to be working on. Okay. Is there a
flow between the four chapters? And I'll
tell you the four chapters again.
Uh
24 was an investigation of the four
truths. 25, which is what we're doing
this morning, is an investigation of
nirvana. 26 is an investigation of the
12 links of the wheel of life. And 27 is
an investigation of how you look at
things. Viewpoint, how do you look at
things?
Okay. And
maybe think about it, okay, in the ne
think about it until the next class.
Okay. And then and then think about it
during your Let's think about it. What's
my next class, Tim? Oh,
Tim. No, I mean,
uh, Friday or something.
Saturday. That's too long. You'll forget
about it. Uh how about in the next class
you tell me the flow. Okay. What how do
you see the flow? I'll I'll tell you the
four things that flow again. What's the
first one? Four truths. Second one's
nirvana. Third one's the 12 links. And
then it's how do you view the world?
Okay. And and then we're done with the
most famous book in Buddhism. Okay. That
is the most famous book in in Buddhism I
would say except for the sutras.
There must be a reason why he went
through that flow. There must be a
reason. There must be some deeper
reason. Maybe someone can think about it
before the next class. Okay. All right.
And
next we're going to discuss Nirvana. Uh
Arya Neggina starts to discuss Nirvana.
And don't forget that Arya is at the
very beginning of everything. Okay? Uh
after the Buddha
uh all you have is some Abiid Dharma
stuff going on for 700 years and then
you have Nagaja. Then you have Arya. He
is before the two
brothers. He's before Basandu and Sra.
Okay. He's
before all of the logic schools. He's
before everybody else. Okay. He's he's
the
grandpappa. Okay. He's the mafia don.
All right. And
uh
so when he goes through a topic, it's
very interesting because you're getting
a g a Buddhist genius discussing Lord
Buddha without any help. He's doing it
on his own. He's kind of the first of
he's the first Mahayana teacher. He's
the first bodhicattaki teacher in
history after Lord Buddha. So, uh his
opinion about Nirvana is interesting.
Okay. And it's kind of nice to see
him from for me personally, it's nice to
meet someone who didn't know the
lineage. He started the lineage. Okay.
So, what was his thoughts? He was fresh
off of Buddha. You see what I mean? And
he didn't have 2,000 years of
commentaries. Okay? So, by the way, in
some religions, I would say the longer
it goes on, the more confused it gets.
Uh, and there's weird ideas come in and
weird schools and problems and things
like that. In Buddhism, the opposite
happened. uh the more centuries that
went on, the greater the commentaries uh
and the and the more clear it became.
Buddha spoken riddles and uh and by the
time you get to Tonkapa they have made
it beautifully clear uh exquisitly clear
okay in this lineage uh as it time goes
on things get more amazing okay it's
it's cool it's a cool lineage okay so
anyway here's
uh I call this picture I gave it a name
here today gone tomorrow this is an
American an idiom, you know, here today,
gone tomorrow. Oh, you know, like I
don't know, you meet a cute boy in high
school and you're
like, and then he's gone. Like that life
tends to be a long series of here today,
gone tomorrow. And the way that the
early Buddhists like Abid Dharma people
uh before Vasubandu okay Vasubandu was
at the end of Abid he wrote the summary
of what the school thought after it died
or as it was dying he he wrote the great
Abid Dharma Kosha. But what did they
think before that? What did what did
they think about Nirvana before that?
And it was kind of we call well they
thought your body and your mind what
blinked out just disappeared. Okay.
They thought Nirvana was and by the way
my brother committed suicide and he he
he when he was 20 and he just decided it
was better uh you know he he was had com
he was comfortable he had everything and
uh but he just decided he didn't want to
be he didn't want to exist anymore and
uh so there is this
idea in the lower schools of Buddhism
that nerv Vana means you blink out. You
you kill your body. You kill your mind
and then it's all over and that's kind
of come some kind of happiness. There's
the the the trick is the problem is
what? There's no one to experience
that and they somehow they didn't think
of that. You know, I want to be happy.
Okay. I'm going to kill myself. Okay.
Then you kill yourself. You say who's
happy?
Okay. And that's the neg complaint. It's
like you know is is that nirvana? Is it
nirvana just to blink out you know and
then who who achieves that you know who
reaches that? Who's around to reach it?
You know and and it's doesn't matter at
that point you can't call it happiness.
I think
why there's no one to feel happy. You're
dead. You're gone. Your body is dead.
Your mind is gone. Okay. So they but
this lower
schools
misunderstood the idea of nirvana.
What's nirvana mean
literally.
Okay. Uh n means out. Van means
blow. The word fan comes from van. Okay.
The word like a fan in a in a hot room
is called is v comes from va nir means
out it became nil uh it became negative.
Okay. So it means to blow out. So they
they heard the word nirvana and they
said oh yeah I'll blow out my body and
I'll blow out my mind and then I'll re
I'll be happy. Okay cool. And I think
uh there was a band in the in the in
America called Nirvana and the head of
the band killed himself. And
uh so everybody thought Nirvana must be
like that. It must be how you just kind
of disappear or
something. Okay, that's an old idea of
uh nirvana. Then that developed
later into another idea of nirvana.
Okay. And we call sakche as sakme. Okay.
Sakche and
sakme. And uh early early Buddhists uh
who misunderstood Lord Buddha uh they
said you reach a point of
uh where you're ready to go to Nirvana
but you still have your old body and
mind. Okay. And so you just live in it
until you die and then you reach real
nirvana. Okay. So there's like a
temporary
nirvana. At some point in your ACI
studies, you
reach perfection, personal perfection,
but you're not dead yet. You're still
dragging around the body that
you took on at birth. Okay? So they
don't say you should commit suicide.
They say you should just wait till the
old body wears out and then you'll go to
Nirvana with no remainder with nothing
left over. Okay. So that's you can think
of it you know try to think of it and
and the guardian is addressing this
idea. The guardian historically he's in
a time when everybody around him
believed that you know they said there's
nirvana has two stages. Okay. Why? First
you study, study, study, meditate,
meditate, meditate. And then you stop
all your negativities. Okay? But you're
still in your original body which is
created by bad karma. And you're still
in your original mind which was created
by bad karma. And you took it on at
birth. And then if you can stop doing
bad things, then that old body will
slowly wear out and then you go into
some kind of blink out. Then you blink
out. Okay? So they say there's a period
inside the old body and mind while it's
purifying and then it blinks out and
then that's death. You you die and
everything is smooth. So it's not like
you shoot yourself or something. It's
not like you kill yourself. You stop
making bad
karma. Your old body and mind created by
bad karma wears out and then you reach
nirvana with no remainder. Okay. So they
call it first you have a nirvana with
something left over from your birth and
then later you reach nirvana without
anything left over. So they always put
it into two pieces like that. First,
first you're in
sanssara. You're caught in the wheel of
life. Then you get out of the wheel of
life mentally, but your body hasn't
caught up yet. And that's called nirvana
with something left, with something
lousy left over. And then uh that dies,
that wears out. And then you reach
nirvana with nothing left over. So
that's the lower school's
presentation of Nirvana with something
left over and then later comes Nirvana
with nothing left over. Okay, got it.
Now next picture of
Francisco. I look I got an idiot. I I
I'm sorry. I AI and uh not IR. Um and
I'm sorry.
Uh, and you know, I
spend my wife knows I spend many, many,
many hours every day working on this
stuff. You I tell the AI to do this and
he's
like, and and I spend about half an hour
on one picture and then I say, I'll, you
know, I'll just take it, you know.
Anyway, I said, "Show me a diamond with
a subway running left to right behind
the diamond." And he just couldn't get
it. So, the idea here, okay, there's a
diamond on the subway platform and the
subway is train is moving down the
platform. Okay, got it. So, the train is
approaching the platform. There's a huge
diamond in the platform. The train hits
the diamond level line and then the
train continues beyond past the diamond.
Got it? And that's the higher school's
opinion of nirvana with something left
over and nirvana with nothing left over.
Okay? And they would say, now this is a
very interesting mysterious thing.
They say nirvana with nothing left over
happens
first and then you get to nirvana with
something left over. Okay. So the lower
school is easy. First you have something
left over which is your old body and
mind that you took on and then that
wears out and that dies. That body and
mind dies and then you somehow you're
still around and you reach nirvana.
Okay. And then the higher schools, the
guarder, he says, "You guys got it
wrong. It's the reverse. First you reach
Nirvana with nothing left and then you
reached Nirvana with something left."
Okay, that's very very famous. Okay,
that's a very very famous
uh thing. And the mayor of Rimrock, he's
gonna explain
it. No. Okay.
briefly. So the the nirvana with
something nothing left over means um you
get out of the will of suffering without
body cha and then when you have nana oh
the diamond
what's a diamond
represent
Rob this I don't know if this is a good
system some uh old bodies and mind might
be Yeah. Uh their nirvana with nothing
left over would be the direct perception
of emptiness. Good. And the nirvana with
something left over is going to come out
of the direct perception. Yeah. So so
they would say you know Arya Najger
would say when you see emptiness
directly while you are s while the train
hits the dimemer
uh you are in nirvana with nothing left
over. And then when you come out of
that, you pick the old luggage back up.
You pick the old suitcase back up. You
start seeing things as coming from their
side again. Okay, cool. And there's
that's by the way, that's the ultimate
meaning of Maya in Buddhism. What's
Maya? Maya is the name of Lord Buddha's
ma.
Yeah, her name means illusion. But
illusion means you saw emptiness
directly. You know things are not coming
this way. But then when you come out of
emptiness, you can't rem you can't see
it anymore, but you still remember. Then
that's called kind of a crazy period in
your life because you know you're wrong,
but you can't stop it. Okay. you. It's a
what do you call that? It's a conflicted
thing. Okay. Does the pen come from you?
Yes. Do you see it that way? No. Even
when you teach it, guess Michael. Yeah.
Even when I teach it, I see it as coming
from its
side. Well, just stop it. I can't. Okay.
I'm I'm in Nirvana with remainder. I'm
still carrying the old baggage of my old
mental habits. that I and then that's
why an Arya can get
upset. Okay, that's why an Arya can
complain day after day about not having
enough time.
Okay. Okay. They know it's coming from
them but they can't remember. Okay. All
right. Or they can't see it at that
time. That's why Arya is not an arhot.
That's why an arya still has negative
emotions. Okay.
Arhot, someone who reached nirvana, they
stopped all the seeds to see things
coming from their own side. But an arya
a baby arya or early arry. By the way,
every ar is also an arya. Every Buddha
is also an arya. But generally arry
means a person who had the experience of
emptiness directly but still see things
coming from their own side and cannot
stop themselves. And that that weird
existence for 500 years typically 500
years is called uh illusion that they
understand it's an illusion but they
can't stop it. Okay. And then the slowly
because they saw that everything's
coming from them. Slowly they're able to
stop their anger, desire, jealousy. They
and Arya is improving
fast. That's why they're streaming.
Okay? That's why they're on their way
out. They're improving inexurably
improving. No one can stop it. If they
wanted to stop, they couldn't stop it.
So once you see emptiness
directly, you you know from the first
day that
every I almost said but my wife
is here. Uh every irritating person you
ever meet was coming from you. But you
can't stop being irritated. Okay? Uh and
that's and that's a baby area. And then
they have to work work and then they
become an then they reach nirvana. So
they reach
Nirvana without any baggage first and
then they pick up the baggage again and
struggle with it until they reach our
heart. You see what I mean? Okay, got
it. Okay, we finished that
one. Next
picture. This is called party nirvana.
This is a Vietnamese image actually from
from Vietnam. uh and there's many many
carvings and
statues and and there in English they
say oh Buddha reached his final nirvana
you know and it's a polite way to say he
kicked a bucket in English we say he
died you know uh so they will say they
don't want to say Buddha died so they
say Buddha reached his final nirana and
it always irritated me I said just look
say he died you
No, he raised his fight on the ground,
you know. Yeah.
Um, and and the name of this idiom, the
name of this picture, okay, for all of
ACI future history is par nirvana colon
last chapter in the big act. Last
chapter in the big act. Okay. Lord
Buddha performed 12 miraculous deeds in
his lifetime. Every Buddha, male,
female, Tara performed 12 great deeds in
her last lifetime. Okay? And those are
called the big
act. Says
uh really good at
pretending. Okay? And uh the whole thing
from getting born to growing up in the
palace to seeing the dead men to going
out to the forest to hanging out with
his five friends to sitting under the
booty tree to reaching his
enlightenment to sitting for seven weeks
because no one's going to understand
this and then teaching for the rest of
his life and then laid down and and Hari
Nirvana you know ultim what do you call
final
nirvana it's all a big show okay it's
all a big play and it's played out
countless times on countless worlds okay
many many Buddhas are playing right now
on different planets you
know Karen had this be where are you she
oh she had this beautiful photo that she
took of the Milky way. You know, we are
on the edge of our galaxy. Planet Earth
is on the edge of a
huge circular galaxy of billions and
billions of planets. And it's only from
Diamond Mountain that you can see them.
Uh you you you can we're on the edge of
it. So when you have a really dark
night, right now it's a lousy time to
watch the sky because it's full moon
close to full moon. But on a new moon,
on a black moon here, you could you can
see that we are on the edge of the
galaxy and you can see the rest of the
galaxy from Diamond Mountain. It's very
beautiful. It looks like a strip of
stars, you know. It's
actually like that and we're on the
edge, you know. So on
every they say in a in a one inch square
there's billions and billions of
planets.
So there are billions of Buddhists right
now pretending to get born, pretending
to get educated, pretending to get a
great idea and then pretending to reach
this kind of nirvana. Why I show this
kind of nirvana is I want you to forget
about it. Okay? It's got nothing to do
with nirvana. Okay? Buddha didn't have
to die. Buddha didn't lay down even
though he looks comfortable.
Uh and uh okay so just cancel that in
your list of
nirvanas just forget that one okay
that's all a big show okay all right it
is though a
very important teaching on impermanence
you know and every Buddhist
leader and every Buddhist teacher
u will talk about their own death the
end of their teaching
uh the the end of their time on this
earth. And that's a that's Buddhism. And
I like it. I think it's good. I think to
have a religion where where the leaders
of the religion say, "Look, you're all
impermanent and I am too and let's do
what we can do while we have time
because we won't be here long." You
know, I think it's great. I think it's
beautiful. Okay. I think that that
Buddhist leaders can
say Buddha himself said look I'm going
to
disappear and then my teaching will
disappear in this world and to be so
honest uh about
impermanence that hey guess what
impermanence applies to me too and
impermanence applies to my teaching too
and to speak about it openly to speak
about it honestly
I think it's very healthy for an
organization and for a for Buddhists.
It's it's it's it's healthy to say we're
all in this
together. Uh and we will all disappear
one by one alone. Each person will go
alone and even the teacher will go alone
and the and the teaching will die out.
You know you can do the five houses but
then there'll be four and then there'll
be three and then everybody will say
what five
houses okay and as you create the five
houses it's healthy Buddhism to say I
know they won't last
forever but let's give the world the
five houses for as long as we can okay
and then that will help the world and
I'll meet you in the next live don't be
late you know this song Jimmy Henry
Okay. Uh, six. Uh, next picture. We
still got five minutes. Am I right,
Tim? Right. Oh, we got that thing called
Q&A. Guess I forgot what it is.
Uh,
okay. Next picture.
Yeah. Then Arya Near says, "Look, does
Nirvana last forever?" Okay. Does
Nirvana last forever? Now as a Buddhist
try to understand the contradiction
here. You have to trigger, you have to
create, you have to give birth to your
nirvana and then it's going to last
forever and you won't pop out of
nirvana which means come back to a dead
body. You see what I mean? Do you get
the get the get the
problem? All things which have causes
die. All things which are created come
to an end. So the other guy's like,
"What about Nirvana, Mr. Arya Nagaraja?"
You know, can you achieve Nirvana? Yes.
Does that mean you didn't have it and
then you had it? Yes. Does that mean you
did something to make it happen? Yes.
Then how the hell can you stay there
forever? Then it then it's impermanent.
You you your big teaching Mr. Buddha or
Mr. Near your big teaching is anything
that has a cause will end. Then how come
we don't pop out of
Nirvana? How can you stand nirvana
forever? That that there's no such
thing. You you thought there's no such
thing. How can you achieve a thing which
lasts forever? There's no such thing.
Okay, that's pretty cool, right? It's a
pretty good complaint. Iron
[Music]
sl okay and you can chew on it in your
retreat. Okay, I'll give you a
clue. And by the way, the next topic
we're going to cover is the wheel,
right? The 12 links of the wheel. Uh
so we talk about dependence. There's a
big deal in Buddhism. Uh everything is
dependent. Everything depends on
something else. Right? And there's two
kinds of dependence. All right? Number
one, all things depend on their causes.
Okay? All changing things, all changing
things depend on their causes. So I
don't know, rice depends on rice seed.
Wheat depends on wheat seed. Corn
depends on corn
seed. Depends on
the I'm not as good as Jasmine, but I
learned one word for every hundred words
she learned.
Anyway, that's one kind of dependence.
Okay. And by the way, the lower schools
are kind of obsessed by that kind of
dependence. Cause and effect. Okay.
What's dependent origination? All things
start in dependence on other things.
Okay. And then you have to appreciate
that there's a higher dependent
origination. Okay. And that's that all
things depend on your
perceptions. Okay. All things depend on
on your how you see them. Okay. All
things depend on
names or all by the way when you say the
higher dependent
origination doesn't mean all things come
from causes. It means all things come
from your perceptions. Okay? All things
come from your seeds. Okay? All things
come from names. Okay? And there's a big
deal about names and
labels and and all I want you to
remember, okay? And never forget it,
okay? When Buddhism says names, all
things are name only, mind name only,
label, all things are labeled, it means
all things are ice cream with chocolate
sauce. Okay, what's that mean? It means
that we take the parts of a pen, the
tube and the color. We take the shape
and the color. Okay? And then on top of
it, we pour the chocolate sauce. I'm
getting hungry. We pour the chocolate
sauce of the of the pictures that come
out of our mind. And that's dependent
origination. The the higher dependent
origination doesn't mean everything
comes from causes. The higher the real
dependent origination means the world is
all pieces which are put together by
your mental pictures and each person has
different mental pictures. Okay. So each
person is experiencing a different
world. Okay. Uh an
insect for doesn't see a pen. A dog
doesn't see a pen. A human sees a pen.
The parts are the same. The pieces are
the same. Okay. But their mind is has a
new picture on top of that. And that is
timeless. And that is that is not what
you would call cause and effect. Okay?
It is not. That's a
dependence which in a way is beyond time
and is beyond growing and stopping.
Okay? In the moment that is
happening, it's it's beyond time. It is
not uh seeds and sprouts. It is pictures
and parts. And that's beyond time. Okay?
You can have pictures on top of
parts and not talk
about seeds and and sprouts. You see
what I mean? There's two kinds of
dependence in Buddhism. One is over time
the seed causes to sprout. Okay?
That's that's a lower school dependence.
Higher
dependence. Every the pen in a single
moment the pen in a single moment is
just pieces of something that you put
your pictures on and and that's eternal.
That's that happens in a moment. Okay.
That's a the relationship of a whole to
the parts is different than the that
dependence is different from the
dependence of some planting a seed and
then having something grow out of it.
Okay. So which one which one do you
think is are you a guardianous version
of
nirvana? He wants the higher dependent
imagination. He says, "No, you nirvana
is not something that wasn't there and
then was there because you planted the
seed." Nirvana when it happens is a is a
timeless mental picture on timeless
pieces. Therefore, it doesn't come and
go. Therefore, it will not end.
Therefore, you can keep it. Okay? You
got to cook it. Okay? You got to cook
it. You got to cook the difference
between two dependent originations.
Okay? One is easy. You know, kill
somebody, you will be killed. Those who
live by the sword die by the sword.
That's so beautiful. Okay. Uh that's
one. That's cause and effect in one
sense. But the higher cause and effect,
the higher dependence is that you are
surrounded by pieces and you make your
own holes. Each person makes their own
holes according to the pictures that
they have in their mind. Okay, that's
also dependence. Things depend on your
pictures. And that's in in a single
instant. That's in a single instant.
Okay, and that that dependence in a way
is timeless. If you could, if you could
achieve that kind of nirvana, you could
stay there. Got it? Okay. You got to
think cook it. You got to cook it. So,
understand the other guy's problem.
Understand the other guy's complaint and
it's fair and it's a good complaint. How
can you achieve nirvana and stay there?
Because all things with causes have to
end. Then you should pop out of nirvana
after a while. When the seeds were out,
you should pop out of nirvana.
Ah, to reach nirvana in the highest
meaning of dependence means okay to
reach nirvana in the highest meaning of
dependence means that you would have to
create a self perpetuating seed
system. I'll say it again. To reach
Nirvana in the highest idea of
dependence, you would have to
continually create a
self-perpetuating seed system. You'd
have to create a a system where the
energy you put into it is replaced all
the time. And I'll give you an example,
okay? And and don't forget it. All
right?
um in the DCI
system. And by the way, we're gonna be
filming some DCI this week uh at Diamond
Mountain because I have a I have a
surgery. I have a small muscle surgery
here
uh in two weeks or something like that.
So, I can't do the I can't do all the
filming
for SEIM during SCM. So anyway, uh we'll
be doing some filming uh like that.
Okay. So, is it possible to replenish
seeds as you use them? And in DCI, what
we teach is, and it's an interesting
concept, okay? And I don't want you to
ever forget it because it's the answer
to the question here. The answer to the
question here is
uh if you produce seeds for financial
success, okay? Like if you're starting a
little diamond jewelry company with
three people and three
diamonds and you want to reach a company
that's processing 300,000 diamonds every
day that used to own three diamonds and
used to sit we started on half a table.
We rented half a
table. The guy wouldn't let us sit on
the other half of the table.
So, you get you sell something, you make
$100 or you win $100 in the
class. Then what's the answer to the
Nirvana
question? How does this relate to the
question? Reinvest.
Yeah,
reinvest. Reinvest. Okay. Every time you
make some every time you get some result
from your seed
planting, take some of that money and
and donate it somewhere. Okay? And then
that will double again and that will
double again and that will double again
and that's the answer to the nirvana
question. Okay? Every time you do
something good, every time the seed come
the result comes to you, reinvest. And
then that becomes an endless cycle.
Okay? Then you never fall out of
nirvana. You see what I mean? Okay? Got
it? Is there a cause and effect? Yes.
But it's a cycle. It's a self
perpetuating cycle forever. And it's not
like nirvana wears out and you stop
being in nirvana. Okay? If you keep
helping other people, if you keep in
reinvesting the results you get, it just
gets bigger and bigger and bigger. And
and I can tell you, okay, I'm not a
super wealthy person because I always
give it
away. Unfortunately, I give away more
than I get. Uh but what I'm saying is it
just multiplies on itself. Okay? And I
I'm a grandpa. I'm a I'm a real grandpa
now,
right? And uh I can tell you from 50
years of practice, okay, it just gets
bigger and bigger and bigger and you
can't stop it, okay? And nirvana is the
same. Wellinvested nirvana will last
forever and it doesn't matter that it
started with a
seed. Got it? Okay. It's a
self-perpetuating cycle similar to the
sanssara cycle. Okay, I know I'm
supposed to stop, but I'm not gonna. Q&A
gets pushed off again.
Uh, I've been accused of never wanting
to do a Q&A, but it's not true. I just
always have more to say, which my wife
can also confirm. Um, next picture.
There's another kind of nirvana that you
should know about. At least you should
know about it. And guessing from the
background in this picture, what would
you call
it? Natural nirvana. Okay. There's a
there's a kind of nirvana in Buddhism
called natural nirvana. And it's a code
word for emptiness itself. Okay? All
things have a nirvana inside of them.
But it doesn't mean, you know, they
don't have headaches anymore. Okay? The
microphone has natural nirvana. The the
room has natural nirvana. You have
natural nirvana. And and that's a code
word for emptiness itself. Okay? It
doesn't mean end of suffering. Okay? But
obviously there's a deep
connection. All right? Let's see if I
got any more pictures
here. I think that's I think we finished
Nana. Let's see.
Yeah. Oh, one more. Right. 6.25
transistor. Skip that one. Yeah. Here we
go. Last thing. Okay. And I will end on
time without a Q.
The Sanskrit is quite beautiful. Okay.
There's not the slightest difference
between sanssara and
nirana. There's not the slightest
difference between nirvana and
sanssara. And this is very very famous
uh arya naraja talk. Okay. This is very
very famous. And like like Arya
Negarinous teachings on emptiness, this
verse has been misunderstood for 2,000
years. And then you get these weird
Buddhists who say uh Nirvana and
sanssara are the same. Uh therefore I
can just go to parties every night and
get drunk and you know it's all the
same. Hangover and drunk is the same,
you know. And and you you
hear Buddhist schools throughout
history, weird,
uneducated, stupid, negative, mistaken,
suffering people who say, "Oh, the
guardian said Nirvana and ssara the
same. So, you know, I can just do what I
like. I'm I'm beyond
morality. You know, I'm a high yogi. I'm
a real tantrica, you know. I I can I can
kill things and it's a holy thing and I
can do naughty things and that's a good
thing. And you know, you you hear this
kind of thing. Okay. What did for
$100? Impossible. Stop reading my mind.
uh for $100. What did I in the garden
mean when he said Nirvana is sanssara
and sanssara is
nirvana? And that he said by the way he
said means no difference at all. It's
like at all. Chun means no difference at
all.
Okay. Talk loud. as long as as long as I
understand uh so it means that sanssara
cycle and nirvana cycle and as sanssara
starting with the seeds we planting all
over and over that's why it's causing
cycle the bad seeds and then the good
seeds which lead us to nirvana and it
we're going to cycle in nirvana same
pretty much same time that's what he he
meant because it's coming from the seats
okay there's a problem here
Sometimes somebody gives a $200 answer
to a
$100. Have it somewhere here. Yeah,
that's a $200 answer to a $100 question.
Yeah, perfect. Perfect answer. Yeah,
there's two cycles
here and they're both cycles, but one's
a happy cycle and one's a miserable
cycle. Okay, that's all. Please when you
teach nega please teach this verse you
know and tell people wake up you know
neg is not saying you should go get
drunk every night because ssarus is
saying this is this you know please do
your best through the rest of your life
to fight
these stupid ideas about Buddhism. Okay.
All right.
promise. Okay, now you have to do the
other cycle in the bathroom. So, I'll
see you in 15 minutes. 10
30. Oh, okay. I'll see you at 8
8:15. Okay. Thank you.